<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc n="4159"><titleStmt><title>Josiah Dornford an August Wilhelm von Schlegel</title><editor><persName role="Herausgeber"><forename>Jochen</forename><surname>Strobel</surname><affiliation>Philipps-Universität Marburg</affiliation></persName><persName role="Herausgeberin"><forename>Claudia</forename><surname>Bamberg</surname><affiliation>Philipps-Universität Marburg</affiliation></persName><persName role="Technische Koordination"><forename>Radoslav</forename><surname>Petkov</surname><affiliation>Universität Trier</affiliation></persName><persName role="Bearbeiterin"><forename>Olivia</forename><surname>Varwig</surname><affiliation>Philipps-Universität Marburg</affiliation></persName></editor><respStmt><orgName ref="https://www.uni-marburg.de">Philipps-Universität Marburg</orgName><orgName ref="https://www.slub-dresden.de">Sächsische Landesbibliothek - Staats- und Universitätsbibliothek Dresden</orgName><orgName ref="http://kompetenzzentrum.uni-trier.de">Kompetenzzentrum für elektronische Erschließungs- und Publikationsverfahren in den Geisteswissenschaften an der Universität Trier / Trier Center for Digital Humanities</orgName><resp ref="https://www.august-wilhelm-schlegel.de/briefedigital/contact">Mitwirkende</resp></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><persName role="Bearbeiter/in"><forename>Claudia</forename><surname>Bamberg</surname></persName><persName role="Bearbeiter/in"><forename>Hermione</forename><surname>Cook</surname></persName><persName role="Bearbeiter/in"><forename>Olivia</forename><surname>Varwig</surname></persName></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><publisher><persName><forename>Jochen</forename><surname>Strobel</surname></persName><persName><forename>Claudia</forename><surname>Bamberg</surname></persName></publisher><availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/de/">Namensnennung - Nicht-kommerziell - Weitergabe unter gleichen Bedingungen 3.0 Deutschland (CC BY-NC-SA 3.0 DE)</licence><ab type="version">version-01-22</ab><ab type="edition">Digitale Edition der Korrespondenz August Wilhelm Schlegels</ab><ab type="state">Neu transkribiert und ausgezeichnet; zweimal kollationiert</ab></availability><date when="2022-01-26"/><idno type="url">https://www.august-wilhelm-schlegel.de/briefedigital/letters/view/4159</idno></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc n="carrier2"><msIdentifier><institution>Dresden, Sächsische Landesbibliothek - Staats- und Universitätsbibliothek</institution><idno type="signatur">Mscr.Dresd.e.90,XIX,Bd.6,Nr.19</idno></msIdentifier><physDesc><objectDesc><ab type="oai">DE-1a-33442</ab><ab type="alternativeOai">DE-1a-1879266</ab><ab type="alternativeSignatur">Mscr.Dresd.e.90,XIX,Bd.6,S.89-92</ab><ab type="type">Manuscript</ab><ab type="subtype">Original</ab><ab type="pages">4S. auf Doppelbl., hs. m. U.</ab><ab type="paper">23,2 x 18,9 cm</ab><ab type="note">Empfangsort erschlossen.</ab></objectDesc></physDesc></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><correspDesc ref="https://www.august-wilhelm-schlegel.de/briefedigital/letters/view/4159"><correspAction type="sent"><persName key="5691" ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/116187530">Josiah Dornford</persName><placeName key="292" ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/4074335-4">London</placeName><date when="1790-08-22">1790-08-22</date></correspAction><correspAction type="received"><persName key="766" ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118607960">August Wilhelm von Schlegel</persName><placeName key="2" ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/4021477-1">Göttingen</placeName></correspAction></correspDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><facsimile><graphic n="1" decls="carrier2" url="https://digital.slub-dresden.de/data/kitodo/AWvS_DE-1a-33442_Bd.6/AWvS_DE-1a-33442_Bd.6_tif/jpegs/00000089.tif.original.jpg"/><graphic n="2" decls="carrier2" url="https://digital.slub-dresden.de/data/kitodo/AWvS_DE-1a-33442_Bd.6/AWvS_DE-1a-33442_Bd.6_tif/jpegs/00000090.tif.original.jpg"/><graphic n="3" decls="carrier2" url="https://digital.slub-dresden.de/data/kitodo/AWvS_DE-1a-33442_Bd.6/AWvS_DE-1a-33442_Bd.6_tif/jpegs/00000091.tif.original.jpg"/><graphic n="4" decls="carrier2" url="https://digital.slub-dresden.de/data/kitodo/AWvS_DE-1a-33442_Bd.6/AWvS_DE-1a-33442_Bd.6_tif/jpegs/00000092.tif.original.jpg"/></facsimile><text><body><div><p><hi rend="family:Courier"><milestone unit="start" n="26946"/>[1]</hi><note type="Notiz_zur_Transkription"><title>Paginierung des Editors</title></note><milestone unit="end" n="26946"/><hi rend="family:Courier"> Dear Schlegel<lb/>It is with no small degree of pleasure I assure you that I seize an hours leizure to devote to an undeservedly neglected friend; for as such I am sure you will think I have treated you, by not writing to you sooner; although I hope I need not use any arguments to convince you that my neglect has been undesigned. I am exceedingly obliged to you for the kind letter you sent me when my Servant returned from <placeName key="2">Göttingen</placeName>, and am happy to hear that <persName key="4058">my young friend</persName>, whom I recommended to your care has answered the character I was authorized to give of him from personal acquaintance, and the general opinion of his friends.. It is no small satisfaction to me to have in any respect contributed to gratify the desire which you often expressed of being placed in such a situation when I had the pleasure of conversing with you on the subject. The letter you lately sent to <persName key="10397">Mrs Smith</persName> has given you a very high place in her esteem, and your account of <persName key="4058">her son</persName> is very satisfactory. I hope he will continue to profit from his very eligible situation, and remember <milestone unit="start" n="43538"/>that it the</hi><note type="Notiz_zur_Transkription"><title>Lies: that it is the</title></note><milestone unit="end" n="43538"/><hi rend="family:Courier"> fortunate lot of few of his countrymen, at his years to enjoy such peculiar advantages. I often regret that I did not pass the younger years of my life at Göttingen instead of <placeName key="3530">Oxford</placeName>, because an ambitious mind is gratified there by being reputed studious, whilst with us a man who devotes his time to books is too frequently treated with contempt. I was much pleased a short time since with a letter written in your favour by </hi><persName key="4996">Hofrath<hi rend="family:Courier"> Zimmerman</hi></persName><hi rend="family:Courier"> of <placeName key="173">Hanover</placeName>, who seems to have your welfare very much at heart. It was written to a particular friend of mine, who sent it for the perusal of <persName key="2714">Mr Smith</persName>. I <milestone unit="start" n="26947"/>[2]</hi><note type="Notiz_zur_Transkription"><title>Paginierung des Editors</title></note><milestone unit="end" n="26947"/><hi rend="family:Courier"> have lately received a long letter from <persName key="11790">your friend Arenhold</persName> from <placeName key="133">Kiel</placeName>. He appears to be very happy in his situation, which I am glad to hear for he is a very deserving young man. My time has been entirely occupied for these last ten months with printing <name key="11783" type="work">my translation of <name key="12869" type="work"><persName key="5310">Pütters</persName> book</name></name> I have corrected the Press myself, which I have found the most tedious and unpleasant work I ever was engaged in, particularly the index, which I have been often tempted to leave with all its errors. I have often thought of the difficult task you must have had in preparing the index for <name key="11782" type="work"><persName key="257">Mr Heynes</persName> <persName key="3189">Virgil</persName></name>, which has astonished all our Literary men. I suppose you have heard that it will be reprinted in a very splendid manner in <placeName key="292">London</placeName>. The edition will certainly be very profitable to the booksellers – I wish I could say that it would be profitable to the learned, and worthy Professor to whom they are so much </hi><hi rend="family:Courier;overstrike:1">obliged</hi><hi rend="family:Courier"> indebted. I am glad to hear that <persName key="11784">Völkersahm</persName> is well I have a great respect for the qualities of his heart and head, and feel interested in his welfare. When you write to him again I beg you will remember me to him in the most friendly manner. Is it true that <persName key="1402">Bürger</persName> is married? <persName key="2568">Drake</persName> told me lately that one of <name key="8372" type="work">his Poems</name> had proved an arrow in the breast of <persName key="4815">his present Lady</persName>, and that a similarity of genius was the occasion of their union. <name key="3239" type="periodical">The <placeName key="98">Hamburg</placeName> papers</name>, which I take in, to hear some German News, mention a dispute between the Students and tradesmen of <placeName key="2">Gottingen</placeName>. I hope it was not of a very serious nature. We had a dispute of that kind once at <placeName key="3530">Oxford</placeName> in which several lives were lost. I am told that <persName key="11785">Count Broglio</persName> is gone to finish his studies at <placeName key="22">Leipsic</placeName>. He must be in a very unpleasant predicament, considering the present state of affairs in France. It is a happy circumstance for many of the unfortunate fugitives, that they retain their volatile dispositions in the midst of their distress. They seem but little affected, if I may judge from those I have been in company with here <milestone unit="start" n="26948"/>[3]</hi><note type="Notiz_zur_Transkription"><title>Paginierung des Editors</title></note><milestone unit="end" n="26948"/><hi rend="family:Courier"> by the losses they have sustained by the revolution. </hi><hi rend="family:Courier">Our Theater Coffee Houses, and public walks are crowed with chearful </hi><hi rend="family:Courier;underline:1">Aristocrats</hi><hi rend="family:Courier"> who are as vociferous and gay, as if they visited <placeName key="292">the metropolis of England</placeName> merely for amusement, although many of them poor fellows! are scarcely able to support themselves</hi><hi rend="family:Courier">, and such a number of valuable Jewels of their distinguished Nobles even, are exposed to sale at the windows of very inferior Pawn brokers, that the newspapers say the price of Diamonds is considerably decreased I know not whether you ever saw a character of the French by the late <persName key="11780">Lord Littleton</persName>, which is very descriptive<lb/></hi><name key="11781" type="work"><hi rend="family:Courier">A nation here I pity and admire,</hi></name><hi rend="family:Courier"><lb/>Whom noblest sentiments of glory fire;<lb/>Yet taught by customʼs force, and bigot fear,<lb/>To serve with pride, and boast the yoke, they bear;<lb/>Whose nobles born to cringe, and to command,<lb/>In Courts a mean, in camps a generous band;<lb/>From each low tool of powʼr content receive,<lb/>Those laws their dreaded arms to Europe give,<lb/>Whose people, vain in want, in bondage blest,<lb/>Thoʼ plunderʼd, gay; industrious thoʼ oppressʼd<lb/>With happy follies rise above their fate,<lb/>The jest and envy of each wiser State.<lb/>They may change their government, and system of politics; but it certainly will not be in this century that they lose their levity.<lb/>I wish I could give you some interesting information respecting English Literature. I suppose you have seen </hi><name key="12818" type="work"><hi rend="family:Courier">the five celebrated Quartos of </hi><persName key="12817"><hi rend="family:Courier">Mr Bruce</hi></persName><hi rend="family:Courier"></hi></name><hi rend="family:Courier">, </hi><persName key="11786"><hi rend="family:Courier">Peter Pindar</hi></persName><hi rend="family:Courier"> our famous Satyrist, and if I may so express myself, Literary Bull Dog, has attacked him violently. His motto is Wonders! Wonders! Wonders! </hi><persName key="12819"><hi rend="family:Courier">A gentleman generally known here by the name of the Walking Stewart</hi></persName><hi rend="family:Courier"> has lately published two volumes, called </hi><name key="11787" type="work"><hi rend="family:Courier">Travels to discover <milestone unit="start" n="43542"/>the<note type="Notiz_zur_Transkription"><title>Abkürzungszeichen, das hier wohl "the" meint</title></note><milestone unit="end" n="43542"/> Source of Moral motion</hi></name><hi rend="family:Courier">, Such an eccentric mixture has not appeared this age. He has literally visited most parts of the habitable world on foot, &amp; lived among the various natives in their Palaces, and Cottages – Many of his remarks are pertinent and new <milestone unit="start" n="26949"/>[4]</hi><note type="Notiz_zur_Transkription"><title>Paginierung des Editors</title></note><milestone unit="end" n="26949"/><hi rend="family:Courier"> and as he is not a man of reading his style is almost as novel as his sentiments.<lb/>You will much oblige me by desiring <persName key="644">Diederich the bookseller</persName> to send me <name key="2744" type="periodical">the new Almanack</name>, which contains <name key="4986" type="work"><persName key="88">Schillers</persName> history of the thirty years war</name>, </hi><hi rend="family:Courier;offset:4"><name key="12872" type="work"><persName key="12484">Buschings</persName> acct of <persName key="1094"><milestone unit="start" n="43541"/>the<note type="Notiz_zur_Transkription"><title>Abkürzungszeichen, das hier wohl "the" meint</title></note><milestone unit="end" n="43541"/> King of Prussia</persName></name></hi><hi rend="family:Courier"> and the </hi><hi rend="family:Courier;underline:1">first</hi><hi rend="family:Courier"> vol of <name key="11788" type="work"><persName key="5310">Putters</persName> History of <orgName key="6154">the University of <placeName key="2">Göttingen</placeName></orgName></name>, I have the second, which has several references to the other. I wish to have it soon, as a friend of mine has requested I will procure him a list of <name key="12873" type="work">all <persName key="257">Mr Heynes</persName> publications</name> which are there enumerated. I should like very much to have <name key="19" type="periodical">the Göttings: Gelehr: Anzeig.</name> every week if it could be sent by means of the Secretary at <placeName key="173">Hanover</placeName>. Will you be so good as to speak to Diederich about it, and desire him at the same time to send me his account, &amp; an order for the payment of it. I dare say <persName key="541">our friend Tatter</persName> would have the goodness to forward the Anz: for me. If he can, I should like to begin with it in November when I settle in <placeName key="292">London</placeName> for the winter Pray inform me of any interesting German publications, which any of your friends among the Professors wish to have noticed in our English reviews. </hi><hi rend="family:Courier;overstrike:1">Pray</hi><hi rend="family:Courier"> Make my respectful compliments to all my old Friends, particularly to those families, from whom I experienced such civilities, as <persName key="257">Mr Heyne</persName> <persName key="3404">Feder</persName> <persName key="2770">Michaelis</persName> &amp; <persName key="2734">Schlötzers</persName>. Are none of <persName key="249"><persName key="23"><persName key="9229">the Ladies</persName></persName></persName> married? I often look in <name key="3239" type="periodical">the <placeName key="98">Hamburg</placeName> papers</name> for thy, Heyne, Schlözer or Michaelisʼs name. Remember me to <persName key="4058">Mr Smith</persName> who I hope has received my letter, and to <persName key="2254">Arnswald</persName>, <persName key="1402">Bürger</persName>, </hi><persName key="541"><hi rend="family:Courier;offset:4">Tatter</hi></persName><hi rend="family:Courier"> and <persName key="2709">our old friend Möller</persName>, &amp; believe me I am with great regard<lb/>Your sincere Friend<lb/>Josiah Dornford<lb/></hi><placeName key="11789"><hi rend="family:Courier">Lincolns Inn</hi></placeName><hi rend="family:Courier"> Augt 22. 1790.<lb/>I write in English for <milestone unit="start" n="43539"/>the</hi><note type="Notiz_zur_Transkription"><title>Abkürzungszeichen, das hier wohl "the" meint</title></note><milestone unit="end" n="43539"/><hi rend="family:Courier"> same reason you profess to write in German &amp; I believe most people express their sentiments best in their native language – Do me the favour to forward <milestone unit="start" n="43540"/>the</hi><note type="Notiz_zur_Transkription"><title>Abkürzungszeichen, das hier wohl "the" meint</title></note><milestone unit="end" n="43540"/><hi rend="family:Courier"> inclosed letter to <persName key="11790">Arenhold</persName> at <placeName key="133">Kiel</placeName>. I intend writing by this or the next Post to <persName key="4816">Mr De Launay</persName></hi></p></div></body></text></TEI>
